Let's now get into some details on these data
types. I'm back in the sales.salesorderheader
table, and we want to see why these data
types have been chosen for these columns.
Integer columns can have numbers ranging from
approximately negative to positive two billion.
Small integer numbers range
from -32767 to positive 32767.
Tiny integers range from zero to 255. If
you know a number range will be smaller,
you may want to use a smaller number value
to use fewer bytes overall for storage.
For money fields, the number range is about
negative 922 to positive 922 trillion,
which, of course, is huge. Smallmoney values range
from negative to positive 214000. For text fields,
we covered elsewhere the number of bytes
varchar fields use versus nvarchar fields.
That said, nvarchar fields allow for Unicode
characters while varchar fields do not.
Two columns in this table show this well. This
CreditCardApprovalCode column uses varchar.
There is no need for symbols in this column.
Let's contrast that with the Comment column,
which is an nvarchar column. Someone posting
comments may want to include Unicode symbols,
hence the need for nvarchar even though nvarchar
columns use almost double the space of varchar
columns. For date and time fields, the datetime
field has a date range of 1753 to 9999 in years,
and time can be calculated to the thousandth of a
second. Just to compare, the smalldatetime field
has a date range of 1900 to 2079, specifically
June 6, 2079. More importantly, time can be
broken down to the second but no further. A bit
field, shown here with the OnlineOrderFlag field,
is a 0 or 1 field and is usually used as a Boolean
field, otherwise known as a Yes/No field or a
True/False field. To recap, the type of data you
need to store in a column and the range of data or
the characters of data stored in a column dictates
the data type you will use. You will want to make
sure you choose a data type that stores the data
you need while using as few bytes as possible.